# Md. Masrul Mollah ACA ACMA

- +88(0)1739573935 masrulmollah@gmail.com
  - https://www.linkedin.com/in/masrulmollah/

#### **SUMMARY**

Certified Chartered Accountant of ICAEW and ICAB and Certified Management Accountant of CIMA with 9.5 years of working experience including 4.5 years in Big-Four KPMG and 5 years in Unilever.

Experienced in finance business partnering specially supply chain finance including procurement finance, logistic finance, business waste, supply chain savings, supply chain controls and performance management with track record of achievements in delivering highest savings consecutively for 3 years, performing data analytics, reducing business waste, establishing controls and governance and developing performance management mechanism.

Also experienced in financial accounting & auditing, taxation and transfer pricing. Digital skills include, data science and machine learning with Python and PowerBI.

<ul> <li>PROFESSIONAL EXPERTISE</li> <li>Finance business partner</li> <li>Logistic finance</li> <li>Supply chain controls</li> <li>Supply chain forecasting</li> </ul>	<ul><li>Supply chain finance</li><li>Supply chain savings</li><li>Performance management</li><li>Supply chain accounting</li></ul>	<ul> <li>Procurement Finance</li> <li>Business waste management</li> <li>Data analytics and visualization</li> <li>Audit and Accounting Standards</li> </ul>			
PROFESSIONAL CERTIFICATION	N				
Associate Chartered Accountants (ICAEW) Associate Chartered Management Accountant (CIMA) Associate Chartered Accountant (ICAB)		2018 2016 2015			
			EDUCATION		
			Khulna University		2011

## PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

# Unilever Bangladesh Limited Manager Central Supply Chain Finance

Bachelor's Degree - Business Administration (Major: Finance)

April 2018 – Present

- Procurement finance partner: analyzing material cost and P&L impact, managing gross & net inflation, finding opportunities and savings, forecasting material rate, reviewing cost models and negotiations
- Logistic finance partner: ensuring performance management, performing analysis and finding savings, ensuring controls, maintaining logistic cost accounting, forecasting logistic cost, reviewing cost models and negotiations
- Savings project lead: driving all material and logistic savings projects to fuel the margin and growth by ensuring review, governance, network management, analysis and opportunity identification
- Business waste management lead: conducting root causes analysis, achieving waste avoidance savings and establishing proceed to reduce waste generation, ensuring regular review and governance
- Driving business cases: assessing localization business case and import opportunities, depot capacity remodeling and distribution remapping
- Monitoring demurrage: ensuring regular monitoring and review, ensuring recovery and establishing reduction process
- Performance management: ensuring KPIs and target establishment and practice, regular review and achievement reconciliation for both procurement, logistic and business waste areas
- Controls and governance: establishing controls and governance for both procurement, logistic and business waste and ensuring through monthly audit & report circulation and review

## Major achievements:

- Derived 800+ material and logistic savings projects with highest savings for consecutively 3 years
- Developed logistics cost analytics and standardized KPIs and review process
- Established awareness and process to reduce port demurrage by 50%
- Achieved highest business waste avoidance savings and conducted deep dive and analytics to identify root causes
- Established business waste generation reduction process, early warning system and savings mechanism
- Developed inbound stock management process
- Achieved highest logistic savings for consecutively 3 years
- Developed PowerBI analytics and dashboard in all areas
- Working as lead for fixed assets digitalization project
- Working as lead of one supply chain leadership forum project for business waste

## Unilever Bangladesh Limited Manager Taxation Assistant Manager Taxation

March 2017 – March 2018 October 2015 – February 2017

- Corporate Income Tax: computation, submission, finalize assessment and documentation.
- Transfer pricing: documentation as required by regulation and preparation of statements
- Distributors' Value Added Tax: compliance management by support, guidance and consultation with documents
- Advance Income Tax and Withholding Tax: appropriate deduction, deposit, return submissions
- Tax and VAT authority: management by appeal and ADR procedures on Tax and VAT cases
- System Implementation (SAP): implementation of any changes by Finance Act
- Finance Act proposals: preparation & lobby to pursue business benefit, operational simplification, and fair competition
- Tax and VAT planning: analysis and preparation for Tax and VAT planning at contract stage and project stage
- Tax accounting: accounting for current tax, potential tax, deferred tax, AIT and withholding Tax
- Global Tax: reporting for all global tax reports and working global tax projects

## **Major achievements:**

- Resolved tax cases up to appellate tribunal level
- Proposed AIT rate reduction and lobbied and achieved significant Tax savings
- o Prepared for new VAT law implementation
- Maintained VAT compliance of the distributors
- o Ensured transfer pricing documentation and compliance for 3 years
- Ensured corporate tax and distributor VAT compliance for 3 years
- Developed treasury challan and monthly report automation process
- Implemented global project Tax Calculation Framework (TCF)
- o Established Tax documentation process and guideline
- Training and awareness for the team and other teams

## KPMG Bangladesh Associate Accountant

Trainee Accountant

November 2014 – September 2015 July 2011 – October 2014

- Financial statements preparation and review
- Planning and carry out audit/review engagements
- Corporate and personal Income Tax: compliance, advisory, planning and reporting
- Indirect Tax (Value Added Tax): compliance, advisory and planning
- Due diligence on Income Tax and Indirect Tax (VAT): audit and reporting
- Plan and perform appeal procedure at commissioner and tribunal stages

## Major achievements:

- Consulted major business operations, business development and discontinuation
- o Resolved tax cases up to appellate tribunal level
- Conducted due diligence audit for major business merger and acquisition
- Worked as senior team member in full-scope audits under ISA and IFRS for multinational companies
- Ensured corporate tax and VAT compliance of multinational companies

## **DIGITAL SKILLS**

- Programming language Python, JavaScript, and HTML
- Data analytics and visualization (Python, PowerBI, MS Excel and PS PowerPoint)
- Machine learning models and algorithms (Python)
- Natural Language processing and sentiment analysis machine learning model (Python)
- Business App for data and report with PowerApps
- Office 365 (Office Outlook, Teams, SharePoint, OneDrive etc.)
- Fixed assets management digitalization

## Major achievements:

- Developed PowerBI dashboards for business waste, logistic cost, savings and material inflation
- Developed machine learning models for takeback prediction (linear regression), savings projects implementation prediction (logistic regression) and performance wise logistic lane clustering (Kmeans clustering)
- o Developed NLP-sentiment analysis machine learning model for Youtube and Facebook comments analysis
- Developed supply chain finance data app with PowerApps
- Developed personal website with HTML and JavaScript